Guide to the Anderson Family Papers, 1859-1929
Department of Special Collections
Anderson Family Papers,
1859-1929
Special Collections M0111
Anderson family.
3 linear ft. (ca. 250 items).
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Robert Van Vleck Anderson, 1965.
Scope and Content
This collection is an addition to M0051, the original gift of Mrs. Robert Van Vleck Anderson. These papers are closely related to the first collection and contain many letters by Melville Best Anderson, as well as drafts of letters by Dr. Anderson, a category found in limited numbers in the first collection. There are also photographs, pamphlets, and manuscripts of writings.
Containers 4-6 house the sermons of Edward Coffin Anderson, who was the father of Melville Best Anderson.
Biographical Note
Family of Scottish-English origins which came to the United States in the middle of the nineteenth century. The family settled on the East Coast, later moving West; the Andersons contributed to society in the fields of theology, education and literature. Melville Best Anderson was an author, translator and teacher whose particular interest was the work of Dante. From 1891-1910, he taught in the English Department at Stanford University, serving as first chairman of the department.
Container List
- Letters from Anderson to: (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1) Professor Norton, April 18, 1908
  - 2) Henry Holt, May 31, 1908
    Preparing translation of Dante
  - 3) Professor Norton, June 12, 1908
    Regarding Dante
  - 4) Dear Sir, July 18, 1908
  - 5) Dr. Jordan, November 8, 1908
  - 6) Dear Sir--Protests against Hetch-Hetchy, December, 1908
  - 7) Revised letter [UNK]
  - 8) Miss Myrtle E. Harris, May 2, 1909
    Praise of her dissertation on Shakespeare
  - 9) Mr. Muir (John), May 2, 1909
    Invitation to visit
  - 10) Friend F.F. Browne, May 2, 1909
  - 11) Mr. McClure (publisher), May 28, 1909
  - 12) Publishing Department of MacMillan Co., August 25, 1910
  - 13) Marchese Viviani, December 11, 1911
  - 14) Leopoldo Bucciolini, [UNK]
  - 15) Waldo Browne, September, 1915
    Publisher of Dial C? (Son of Francis Fisher Browne)
  - 16) Capitano Cesare Andreoni, September, 1915
  - 17) Lena Anderson (Mrs. M.B.), October 14, 1915
  - 18) Lena Anderson, October 14, 1915
    Redraft of 17
  - 19) Helen Anderson (niece), November 19, 1915
  - 20) Dr. Henry S. Pritchard, November 20, 1915
    Pres. Carnegie Foundation
  - 21) Edward P. Anderson, December 4, 1915
  - 22) Waldo Browne, January 11, 1916
  - 23) Waldo Browne, January 14, 1916
  - 24) Poem--Christmas card, January 16, 1916
  - 25) Waldo Browne, January 18, 1916
  - 26) Dr. David Starr Jordan, February 16, 1916
  - 27) Waldo Browne, April 1, 1916
  - 28) Waldo Browne, April 4, 1916
    On purchasing Dial, etc.
  - 29) Mrs. Emlin McClair, April 8, 1916
    On her bereavement
  - 30) Waldo Browne, May 3, 1916
  - 31) Miss May, May 31, 1916
    Miss Editn May, relief worker--offers little poem to be sold for War Benefit--Great Refusal
  - 32) Miss Heywood, May 31, 1916
    Mentions plan of poem, asks her help to distribute poem in Paris
  - 33) Robert Anderson, June 1916
    Mentions above poem
  - 34) Edith May, June 11, 1916
    Mentions poem
  - 35) Anna Strunsky Walling, June 13, 1916
  - 36) Reverend Sydney B. Snow, June 13, 1916
  - 37) Robert Anderson, June 15, 1916
    Discusses letter he wrote Mrs. Hoover concerning poem
  - 38) Letter (copy) possibly to Mrs. Hoover, June 23, 1916
  - 39) John S. Phillips, June 23, 1916
    Concerning poem
  - 50) Copy of letters addressed to friends concerning poem, June 24, 1916
  - 41) Revision of above, June 1916
  - 42) Robert Anderson, August 1916
    Sale of poem to F.W.E. Fund
  - 43) Miss Heywood, August 6, 1916
    Part of letter
  - 44) Professor Howard J. Hall, September 4, 1916
  - 45) Waldo Browne, September 4, 1916
  - 46) David Starr Jordan, September 4, 1916
    Reply to letter
  - 47) Robert Anderson, September 5, 1916
    Adds money made by sale of poem, etc.
  - 48) Waldo Browne, September 5, 1916
    Revision of Sept. 4 letter? Failure of Browne to retrieve Dial
  - 49) Mrs. Culver, September 6, 1916
  - 50) Maude Jay Wilson, September 6, 1916
  - 51) Professor Katherine M. Graydon, September 20, 1916
  - 52) Professor William F. Bade, concerning his writing a biography [UNK] Muir. Offers articles, September 20, 1916
  - 53) Miss Heywood, October 8, 1916
  - 54) Mrs. Katherine Nash Thomas, concerning poem, October 16, 1916
  - 55) Prof. Howard J. Hall, October 23, 1916
  - 46) Senor Commendador, October 23, 1916
  - 57) A. Beaumont (correspondent of Daily Telegraph), October 28, 1916
  - 58) Miss McClain, November 17, 1916
    Acknowledge her donation
  - 59) Mrs. Wilson, October 1916
  - 60) Poem to Gordon Craig, 1916
  - 61) Professor Smith, February 27, 1917
    Sends poem on Dante
  - 62) Caspar W. Hodgson, October 9, 1923
    Explains that John Henry Nash wishes to print Anderson's translation of Dante Asks permission of Hodgson (World Book)
  - 63) Mr. Nash, January 1925
    Thanks for gift, Heathen China
  - 64) Prof. Tatlock--list of published books, April 6, 1925
  - 65) Robert Anderson--letter unfinished, April 6, 1925
  - 66) Ray Lyman Wilbur, ND
- Letters from Catherine Merrill: (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 67) February 14, 1881
  - 68) Appreciates having Ida there to teach, February 18, 1881
  - 69) Visit to Vermont and discussion of books, September, 1881
  - 70) Discusses the Andersons living at Butler College, February 18, 1883
  - 71) Discusses new books, June 18, 1883
  - 72) Rejoices that he is at Knox and receives promotion, August 15, 1883
    She will resign from Butler, will lecture
  - 73) Concerning Kate, her niece, December 21, 1884
  - 74) Discusses books-- Pattison's power of growth by experience and reading, August 27, 1885
  - 75) Hears of Anderson's going to Purdue, July 2, 1886
  - 76) Discusses a [UNK] which Anderson is to conduct, January 26, 1887
  - 77) Invitation to tea, March [UNK], 1887
  - 78) Invitation to lecture, May 1, 1887
  - 79) Newsy letter!, May 17, 1887
    Discusses books
  - 80) Sorry he's going West (Iowa,) but feels he is wise; need of growth, July 15, 1887
  - 81) Condolence for Father's illness--, September 3, 1887
    Mentions meeting Edward Everett Hale
  - 82) Describes Bass Point, Nahant, Mass., July 15, 1889
  - 83), December 16, 1889
  - 84) Letter for Catherine Merrill by Katherine Graydon, August 1890
    Thanks him for letters and issues of Dial
  - 85) Asks that he call on friend, etc., August 15, 1892
  - 86) Condolence on death of daughter, Gertrude, October 24, 1892
  - 87) Sorry she wrote obituary for Gertrude--not good, she thought, November 24, 1892
  - 88) Tells of Janet's melancholia, June 17, 1893
  - 89) Hopes Anderson will visit her, June 27, 1893
  - 90) Invitation to visit her, discuss books, May 9, 1894
    Believes Janet recovering
  - 91) Thanks him for pictures sent from Palo Alto Discusses books, July 17, 1894
  - 92) Condolence for another death, April 1895
  - 93) Asks for references for her talk on The Child in Literature, January 12, 1896
  - 94) Thanks him for references, February 7, 1896
  - 95) Wonders if Anderson would consider cousin, Katherine Merrill, for assistant, April 6, 1896
  - 96) Thanks for Dial, December 1, 1896
    Would like references for Eber for Mrs. Butler
  - 97) Thanks for poem, picture of San Francisco Bay, etc., January 22, 1898
  - 98) Contemplates his visit, December 2, 1899
  - 99) Asks him to give talk on French Literature
  - 100) Delighted he'd come
  - 101) Further arrangements
  - 102) Further arrangements
  - 103) Disappointed she cannot visit Anderson
  - 104) Glad to see his article in Dial
  - 105) Regrets not calling on his mother
  - Postcards--6
  - In Memoriam
  - Literary Criticism by Catherine Merrill
- Miscellaneous Letters (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 106) A. H. Barnhill (real estate), January 1926, April 1926
  - 107) Ellen Weir Cathcart, October 29, 1901
  - 108) Katherine Weir Dorsey, September 1, 1901
  - 109) Katherine Graydon, July 26, 1883
  - 110) Katherine Graydon, February 26, 1885
  - 111) Katherine Graydon, May 22, 1891
  - 112) Katherine Graydon, May 21, 1891
  - 113) Mary M. Graydon, March 8, 1885
  - 114) Mary M. Graydon, August 14, 1887
  - 115) Guglielmo La Wadon, December 12, 1916
  - 116) Kate Merrill to Catherine Merrill-- send to Prof. Merrill, March 16, 1896
  - 117) Mina Merrill, June 29, 1891
  - 118) Mina Merrill, July 2, 1891
  - 119) Mina Merrill, September 23, 1891
  - 120), September 30, 1891
  - 121) Mina Merrill, October 18, 1891
  - 122) Mina Merrill, January 17, 1892
  - 123) S. Merrill, December 4, 1901
  - 124) Charles W. Moores, December 21, 1890
  - 125) Charles W. Moores, September 14, 1890
  - 126) Janet M. Moores, April 17, 1881
  - 127) Janet M. Moores, February 7, 1886
  - 128) Janet M. Moores, April 15, 1888
  - 129) Copies of letters from Rector of University of Paris, March 1920
    Letter from Rector
  - 130) May Aright Sewell, January 28, 1889
  - 131) May Louise Shipp, May 3, [UNK]
  - 132) May Louise Shipp, July 15, 1901
  - 133) May Louise Shipp, August 3, 1901
  - 134) May Louise Shipp, August 7, 1901
  - 135) May Louise Shipp, August 13, 1901
  - 136) May Louise Shipp, September 2, 1901
  - 137) World Book Company, Publishers, August 2, 1921
  - 138) World Book Company, May 11, 1922
  - 139) World Book to John Henry Nash--about Anderson, February 21, 1924
  - 140) Article of Agreement with World Book Co. and Anderson, August 2, 1921
  - 141) World Book Company, August 13, 1929
  - 142) Unfinished letter to Anderson, March 19, 1905
  - 143) Isabelle Higgins
  - 144) To Melville Best Anderson from David Starr Jordan (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 145) Reply to Jordan by Anderson
- Poems and drafts of poems, etc.
  - 146) Poems to others
  - 147) Drafts of poems
  - 148) Poem to son Robert
  - 149) On the founding of a Foundation in memory of Catherine Merrill
  - 150) A Heroic Bit of History
  - 151) Introducing Dr. Hale (Man Without a Country)
  - 152) The Last Word
  - 153) King Arthur and Arthurian Literature
  - 154) Tribute to Anderson by Academic Council
  - 155) Draft on Hamlet
- Dante (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 156) Portraits of Dante by F. M. Mather
  - 157) Notes on Dante
  - 158) Virgil as conceived by Dante
- Miscellaneous notes and articles (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 159) On Henry James
  - 160) Italy's motives in the War
  - 161) Has Hilda a Soul
  - 162) George Gissing
  - 163) Who is W. H. Hudson
  - 164) Conversation of John Muir
  - 165) Balzac--Life and Personal Character
  - 166) Pamela
  - 167) George Sand
  - 168) Chateaubriand--prose epic of Les Natchez
  - 169) Chatterlou--Alfred de Vigny
  - 170) Conversation of John Muir
- Translations
  - 171) Leopardi: The Broom Plant (translation)
  - 172) Hugo: Les Voix Suterieures
  - 173) Schiller's Don Carlos
  - 174) Charlemagne's Sea Voyage
  - 175) Le Martine's Jocelyn--Peasants at the Spring
  - 176) Le Martine's Jocelyn--Human Caravan, Moses, Night, Cavern
  - 177) Song from Roy Blas (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 178) Alfred de Vigny--La Maison du Berger
  - 179) Alfred de Vigny--Mount of Olives
  - 180) Alfred de Musset--La Nuit de Mai (The Mure)
  - 181) Alfred de Musset--December Night
  - 182) Alfred de Musset--Remembrance
  - 183) Alfred de Musset--Rolla
  - 184) Alfred de Musset--Conclusions of a Letter to Lamartine
  - 185) Beranger's Les Fous
  - 186) Flotsam and Jetsam on the Shore of a Memory
  - 187) Description of outing at Pacific Grove-- [UNK]
  - 188) Concerning Ewald Flugel--read in Memorial Chapel, December 8, 1914
  - 189) Translation by Anderson of Grimm's lectures on Goethe. Lectures 1-4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 190) Continuation Lectures 5-7 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 191) Diaries, accounts, etc. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 192) Diaries, accounts, etc. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 193) Photos (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 194) Class Rolls: 1878-1886(not complete) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 195) Class Rolls: 1886-1906
  - 196) From Anderson's Library and Popular Key to Birds, Reptiles (1874) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Diary of Motor Trip-- 1920
  - 197) Film Book--Europe (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gertrude in Death
  - 198) Postcards, College Album, Bookmarks? (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 199) Articles in Dial, Popular Science, Indiana College Ass. Address at laving of cornerstone for Stanford Library, Notes on 50 poems by Browning, Founders Day Address (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 200) Photos and Mementos from Gertrude and Balfour (Box 3, Folder 6)
- E. C. Anderson
  - 201) Baptist quarterlies, (2) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 202) Diary, School Report--Michigan, 1859 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 203) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 204) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 205) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 206) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 207) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 208) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 209) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 210) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 211) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 212) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 213) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 214) Sermons of E. C. Anderson (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 215)Diploma from Nova Scotia (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Diploma from Newton Theological Institute
  - Grand Lodge Masons
  - Mrs. Andersons--honorary member of American Baptist Missionary Union